TED has already persuaded me to change my life in one small way,
لقد اقنعتني (تيد) بتغيير حياتي بطريقة صغيرة واحدة،
by persuading me to change the opening of my speech.
وذلك بإقناعي بتغيير افتتاحية خطابي.
I love this idea of engagement.
أحب هذه الطريقة من الاتفاقيات.
So, when you leave here today,
إذا، عندما تغادر اليوم،
I'm going to ask you to engage or re-engage
سأطلب منكم أن تتفقوا أو تعيدوا الاتفاق
with some of the most important people in your lives:
بأهم الأشخاص في حياتكم:
your brothers and sisters.
أخوانكم وأخواتكم.
It can be a profoundly life-affirming thing to do,
يمكن أن يكون شيئا ايجابيا بحق،
even if it isn't always easy.
حتى إذ لم يكن شيئا سهلا.
This is a man named Elliot,
هذا الرجل يدعى (إليوت)،
for whom things were very difficult.
كانت الأمور صعبة بالنسبة له.
Elliot was a drunk.
كان مدمنا للخمر.
He spent most of his life battling alcoholism,
عاش معظم حياته يحارب الإدمان،
depression, morphine addiction,
الاكتئاب و إدمان المورفين،
and that life ended when he was just 34 years old.
وهذه الحياة انتهت وهو في عمر الرابعة والثلاثين.
What made things harder for Elliot is that his last name was Roosevelt.
ما جعل الأمور أصعب بالنسبة له، هو أن اسمه الأخير كان (روزفلت).
And he could never quite get past the comparisons
ولم يستطع تجاوز المقارنة إطلاقا
with his big brother Teddy,
بينه وبين أخيه الأكبر (تيدي)،
for whom things always seemed to come a little bit easier.
الذي كانت الحياة بالنسبة له أسهل.
It wasn't easy being Bobby, either.
ولم يكن من السهل أن تكون (بوبي) أيضا.
He was also the sibling of a president.
كان شقيق الرئيس.
But he adored his brother, Jack.
وأحب أخيه (جاك).
He fought for him,
وحارب لأجله،
he worked for him.
وعمل لصالحه.
And when Jack died, he bled for him, too.
وعندما مات (جاك)، نزف لأجله أيضا.
In the years that followed, Bobby would smile,
وفي السنين اللاحقة، عندما كان (بوبي) يبتسم،
but it seemed labored.
ولكنها بدت ابتسامة مجهدة.
He'd lose himself in his work,
كان يجهد نفسه بالعمل،
but it seemed tortured.
ولكنه بدا معذبا.
Bobby's own death, so similar to John's,
وكان موت (بوبي) أيضا شبيه بموت (جون).
seems somehow fitting.
يبدو الأمر ملائما بطريقة ما.
John Kennedy was robbed of his young life;
(جون كيندي) حرم من الحياة شابا،
Bobby seemed almost to have been relieved of his.
وبدا (بوبي) مرتاحا عند موته.
There may be no relationship that effects us more profoundly,
ربما لا توجد علاقة تؤثر بنا،
that's closer, finer, harder,
أقرب وأفضل وأقسى
sweeter, happier, sadder,
وأحلى وأسعد وأحزن
more filled with joy or fraught with woe
مليئة بالفرح أو مفعمة بالأسى
than the relationship we have with our brothers and sisters.
كتلك العلاقة التي تجمعنا بأخوتنا وأخواتنا.
There's power in the sibling bond.
هناك قوة في رباط الأخوة.
There's pageantry.
هناك عظمة.
There's petulance, too,
وهناك مشاكسة أيضا.
as when Neil Bush,
مثلما (نيل بوش)،
sibling of both a president and a governor, famously griped,
شقيق لرئيس وحاكم، اشتهر بشكواه،
"I've lost patience for being compared to my older brothers,"
"لقد ضقت ذرعا من مقارنتي بأخوي،"
as if Jeb and George W were somehow responsible
كما لو أن (جيب) و(جورج دبليو) كانا مسؤولين
for the savings and loan scandal and the messy divorce
عن فضائح المدخرات والقروض وطلاقه الفوضوي
that marked Neil in the public eye.
الذي أثر على سمعة (نيل) في أعين العامة.
But more important than all of these things,
ولكن الأمر الأكثر أهمية،
the sibling bond can be a thing of abiding love.
إن رباط الأخوة يمكن أن يكون شيئا من الحب الدائم.
Our parents leave us too early,
يتركنا أبوانا مبكرا،
our spouse and our children come along too late.
ويأتي أزواجنا وابنائنا متأخرين.
Our siblings are the only ones who are with us
وأشقائنا هم من يرافقوننا
for the entire ride.
طيلة الرحلة.
Over the arc of decades, there may be nothing
عبر العقود، لا يوجد شيء
that defines us and forms us more powerfully
يحددنا ويشكلنا بقوة
than our relationship with our sisters and brothers.
أكثر من علاقتنا بشقيقاتنا وأشقائنا.
It was true for me,
كان أمرا حقيقيا بالنسبة لي،
it's true for your children
وهو حقيقي لأطفالكم
and if you have siblings, it's true for you, too.
وإذا كان لديكم أشقاء، هو حقيقي بالنسبة لكم.
This picture was taken when Steve, on the left, was eight years old.
التقطت هذه الصورة عندما كان عمر (ستيف) ،الذي يظهر يسار الصورة، ثمان سنوات فقط.
I was six, our brother Gary was five and my brother Bruce was four.
كان عمري ست سنوات وشقيقنا (غاري) كان عمره خمس سنوات وأخي (بروس) أربع سنوات.
I will not say what year it was taken.
لن أقول في أي سنة تم التقاطها.
It was not this year.
ولكنها ليست هذه السنة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I open my new book, "The Sibling Effect,"
أفتح كتابي الجديد "تأثير الأشقاء"
on a Saturday morning,
في صباح يوم السبت،
not long before this picture was taken,
ليس بوقت طويل قبل التقاط هذه الصورة،
when the three older brothers decided that it might be a very good idea
عندما قرر الثلاثة أخوه أنها فكرة جيدة
to lock the younger brother in a fuse cabinet in our playroom.
أن يحبسوا شقيقهم الأصغر في صندوق الكهرباء في غرفة الألعاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We were, believe it or not, trying to keep him safe.
صدقوا أو لا تصدقوا أننا كنا نحاول ابقاءه آمنا.
Our father was a hotheaded man,
والدنا كان رجلا عصبيا،
somebody who didn't take kindly to being disturbed on Saturday mornings.
شخص لا يتعامل بلطف مع الازعاج في صباحات يوم السبت.
I don't know what he thought his life would be like on Saturday mornings
لا أعلم ما الذي كان يعتقده عن صباحات يوم السبت
when he had four sons,
بينما لديه أربعة أولاد،
ages four years old or younger when the youngest one was born,
أعمارهم أربع سنوات أو أصغر عندما ولد أصغرهم،
but they weren't quiet.
ولكنهم لم يكونوا هادئين.
He did not take to that well.
ولم يحتمل هذا.
And he would react to being disturbed on a Saturday morning
وكان رد فعله حين يتم ازعاجه صباح السبت
by stalking into the playroom
بالدخول إلى غرفة الألعاب
and administering a very freewheeling form of a corporal punishment,
والبدأ بتنفيذ نوع من العقاب الجسدي الحر،
lashing out at whoever was within arms' reach.
حيث يجلد أي شخص منا على مسافة ذراع منه.
We were by no means battered children but we did get hit,
لم نكن أطفالا معنفين ولكننا تعرضنا للضرب،
and we found it terrifying.
ووجدنا الأمر مرعبا.
So we devised a sort of scatter-and-hide drill.
لذا ابتدعنا نوع من تدريبات الانتشار والاختباء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As soon as we saw or heard the footsteps coming,
حالما نسمع صوت وقع أحذيته،
Steve, the oldest, would wriggle under the couch,
(ستيف) أكبرنا كان يختبىء تحت الأريكة،
I would dive into the closet in the playroom,
وكنت أغوص في الخزانة،
Gary would dive into a window-seat toy chest,
(غاري) يختبأ في صندوق بجانب النافذة،
but not before we closed Bruce inside the fuse box.
ولكن ليس قبل أن نخبأ (بروس) داخل صندوق التيار الكهربائي.
We told him it was Alan Shepard's space capsule,
أخبرناه أنها كبسولة (ألان شيبرد) الفضائية،
and that somehow made it work better.
وجعل هذا الأمر أفضل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I dare say my father was never fooled by this ruse.
واتجرأ على القول أن أبي لم يخدع ابدا بهذا.
And it was only in later years that I began to think
وبعدها بسنوات بدأت أفكر
perhaps it wasn't a good idea to squeeze a four-year-old
أنها لم تكن فكرة جيدة أن نضع طفلا بعمر الأربع سنوات
up against a panel of old-style, un-screwable high-voltage fuses.
داخل لوح قديم التصميم وتيار كهربائي عالي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But my brothers and I, even through those unhappy times,
ولكنني أنا وأشقائي حتى خلال هذه الأوقات غير السعيدة،
came through them, with something that was clear and hard and fine:
توصلنا إلى شيء كان واضحا وصلبا وجيدا:
a primal appreciation for the bond we shared.
تقدير للرباط الذي يجمعنا.
We were a unit -- a loud, messy
كنا وحدة...صاخبة وفوضوية
brawling, loyal, loving,
ضوضائية ومخلصة ومحبة
lasting unit.
وحدة دائمة.
We felt much stronger that way than we ever could as individuals.
شعرنا بقوة أكبر مما كنا متفرقين.
And we knew that as our lives went on,
وعلمنا ونحن نكبر،
we could always be able to call on that strength.
أننا نستطيع دوما العودة لهذه القوة.
We're not alone.
نحن لسنا بوحدنا.
Until 15 years ago,
إلى ما قبل الخمسة عشر سنة الماضية،
scientists didn't really pay much attention to the sibling bond.
لم ينتبه العلماء لرابط الأخوة.
And with good reason:
ولسبب جيد:
you have just one mother, you have just one father
لديك أم واحدة فقط، وأب واحد فقط
if you do marriage right, you have one spouse for life.
وإذا تزوجت بشكل صحيح، لديك زوجة واحدة فقط.
Siblings can claim none of that uniqueness.
والأخوة لا يمتلكون حق الانفراد هذا.
They're interchangeable, fungible, a kind of household commodity.
فهم تبادليون و قابلون للاستبدال ونوع من السلعة المنزلية.
Parents set up shop and begin stocking their shelves with inventory,
يفتتح الأباء متجرا ثم يبدأون بملأ الأرفف بالمخزون،
the only limitation being sperm, egg and economics.
والقيود الوحيدة لهذا هي الحيوانات المنوية والبويضات والاقتصاد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As long as you can keep breathing, you may as well keep stocking.
وطالما تستمر بالتنفس، فبإمكانك الاستمرار بملأ الأرفف.
Now, nature is perfectly happy with that arrangement,
الآن، الطبيعة سعيدة بهذه الترتيبات،
because our primal directive here
لأن محركنا الأساسي هنا
is to get as many of our genes as possible into the next generation.
أن ننقل أكبر عدد من جيناتنا للجيل القادم.
Animals wrestle with these same issues, too,
الحيوانات تتصارع من أجل ذات القضايا أيضا،
but they have a more straightforward way of dealing with things.
ولكن لديهم طريقة مباشرة أكثر للتعامل مع هذه الأشياء.
A crested penguin that has laid two eggs will take a good look at them
البطريق ذو العرف تبيض بيضتين ثم تتفحصها جيدا
and boot the smaller one out of the nest,
ثم تخرج الأصغر من العش،
the better to focus her attentions on the presumably heartier chick
لتركز أفضل على صغيرها القوي
in the bigger shell.
في القشرة الأكبر.
A black eagle will allow all of her chicks to hatch
ستسمح أنثى النسر الأسود لصغارها أن تفقس
and then stand back while the bigger ones fight it out with the little ones,
ثم تبتعد وهي ترى الكبار يصارعون الصغار،
typically ripping them to ribbons
عادة يمزقونهم إربا
and then settling back to grow up in peace.
ثم يعودون ليكبروا بسلام.
Piglets, cute as they are,
الخنازير، بظرافتها،
are born with a strange little outward set of pointing teeth,
تولد بأسنان حادة صغيرة غريبة
that they use to jab at one another
ويستخدمونها لطعن بعضهم
as they compete for the choicest nursing spots.
وهم يتصارعون على أماكن الرضاعة.
The problem for scientists
المشكلة بالنسبة للعلماء
was that this whole idea of siblings as second-class citizens
أن فكرة الأشقاء كمواطنين من الدرجة الثانية
never really seemed to hold up.
لم تبدو صلبة.
After the researchers had learned all they could
بعدما تعلم الباحثون كل ما يمكنهم
from the relationships in the family, mothers and other relationships,
من العلاقات في العائلة وعلاقة الأمهات والعلاقات الأخرى،
they still came up with some temperamental dark matter
خرجوا لنا بأمر مظلم غريب
that was pulling at us,
يشدنا،
exerting a gravity all its own.
ويجذبنا بنفسه
And that could only be our siblings.
وهم ما يمكن أن يكون اشقائنا فقط.
Humans are no different from animals.
فالبشر لا يختلفون عن الحيوانات.
After we are born, we do whatever we can
بعد خروجنا لهذه الحياة، نفعل ما يمكننا
to attract the attention of our parents,
لجذب انتباه ابائنا،
determining what our strongest selling points are
نحدد أقوى نقاطنا
and marketing them ferociously.
ونسوقها بقوة.
Someone's the funny one, someone's the pretty one,
فأحدهم الظريف والآخر الجميل،
someone's the athlete, someone's the smart one.
وأحدهم الرياضي والآخر الذكي.
Scientists call this "deidentification."
والعلماء يسمون هذا بـ"التعريف".
If my older brother is a high-school football player --
إذا كان أخي الأكبر لاعب كرة قدم بالثانوية..
which, if you saw my older brother, you'd know he was not --
وإذا رأيتم أخي الأكبر ستعلمون أنه لم يكن كذلك..
I could become a high-school football player, too
كان بإمكاني أن اصبح لاعب كرة قدم أيضا
and get at most 50 percent of the applause in my family for doing that.
وسأحصل على خمسون بالمئة من الهتاف في عائلتي لفعلي هذا.
Or, I could become student council president
أو ربما كان بإمكاني أن اصبح رئيس مجلس الطلبة
or specialize in the arts
أو أتخصص بالفنون
and get 100 percent of the attention in that area.
وأحصل على نسبة مائة بالانتباه في هذا المجال.
Sometimes parents contaminate the deidentification process,
يلطخ الأباء عملية تحديد الهوية هذه في بعض الأحيان،
communicating to their kids subtly or not,
بحيث يوصلونها لابنائهم بمهارة أو بدون مهارة،
that only certain kinds of accomplishments will be applauded in the home.
فبعض الإنجازات فقط ستنال الاعجاب في المنزل.
Joe Kennedy was famous for this,
(جو كيندي) كان مشهورا بهذا،
making it clear to his nine children
وقد وضح الأمر لابناءه التسعة
that they were expected to compete with one another in athletics
فالمتوقع منهم أن يتنافسوا في الرياضة
and were expected to win,
و أن يفوزوا،
lest they be made to eat in the kitchen with the help,
فربما سيجعلهم يتناولون الطعام في المطبخ مع الخدم،
rather than in the dining room with the family.
بدلا من تناوله في غرفة الطعام مع العائلة.
It's no wonder
لا عجب إذا
that scrawny second-born Jack Kennedy fought so hard to compete
أن الأبن الثاني الهزيل (جاك كيندي) حارب بشراسة لينافس
with his fitter firstborn brother, Joe,
(جو) وهو الأبن البكر ذو اللياقة العالية
often at his peril,
مما عرضه للخطر،
at one point, engaging in a bicycle race around the house
في مرحلة ما، تنافسا في سباق على الدراجات حول المنزل
that resulted in a collision costing John 28 stitches.
مما تسبب في تصادم احتاج بسببه (جون) لـ 28 غرزة.
Joe walked away essentially unharmed.
وخرج (جو) من هذا التصادم سليما.
Parents exacerbate this problem further
يفاقم الأباء هذه المشكلة
when they exhibit favoritism,
عندما يبدأون بالمحاباة،
which they do overwhelmingly, no matter how much they admit it.
حيث يمارسون هذا غالبا، مهما انكروا الأمر.
A study I cite in this TIME magazine covering in the book "The Sibling Effect,"
استشهد بمقالة في مجلة التايم في كتاب "تأثير الأخوة"،
found 70 percent of fathers and 65 percent of mothers
وجد في هذه الدراسة أن 70% من الأباء و65% من الأمهات
exhibit a preference for at least one child.
يظهرون تحيزا لطفلا واحدا على الأقل.
And keep in mind here -- the keyword is "exhibit."
وأبقوا هذا في ذهنكم... الكلمة الرئيسية هي "يظهرون".
The remaining parents may simply be doing a better job of concealing things.
بينما باقي الأباء يقومون بإخفاء الأمر جيدا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I like to say that 95 percent of all parents have a favorite,
وأحب أن أقول أن 95% من الأباء لديهم إبن مفضل،
five percent are lying about it.
وخمسة بالمئة يكذبون بشأن هذا الأمر.
The exception is my wife and me.
والاستثناء هو أنا وزوجتي.
Honestly, we do not have a favorite.
صدقا، لا نفضل أحد أبنائنا على الآخرين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's not parents' fault that they harbor feelings of favoritism.
ليس ذنب الأباء أنهم يشعرون بالتحيز.
And here, too, our natural wiring is at work.
وهنا، طبيعتنا تعمل.
Firstborns are the first products on the familial assembly line.
فالابناء البكر هم الانتاج الأول في خط الجمعية العائلية.
Parents typically get two years of investing dollars, calories
يستثمر الأباء عادة سنتين من الدولارات والسعرات الحرارية
and so many other resources in them,
والعديد من الموارد بهم،
so that by the time the second born comes along,
ولذا عندما يأتي الابن الثاني،
the firstborn is already ... it's what corporations call "sunk costs,"
يكون الأبن البكر... ما تدعوه الشركات بـ"التكاليف المهدرة"،
you don't want to disinvest in this one
لا تريد أن تسحب استثمارك من هذا المنتج
and launch the R&amp;D on the new product.
تبدأ بتطبيق البحث والتطوير على المنتج.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what we begin to do is say, "I'm going to lean to the Mac OS X
إذا ما نبدأ بفعله أن نقول "سأستمر في تحسين نظام تشغيل X حاسب ماك
and let the Mac OS XI come out in a couple of years."
حتى يتم انتاج نظام XI بعد سنتين"
So we tend to lean in that direction.
ونستمر في تحسين ذلك الاتجاه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But there are other forces at work, too.
ولكن هناك قوى أخرى تعمل أيضا.
One of the same studies I looked at both here and in the book found that,
أحد الدراسات التي قرأتها هنا وفي الكتاب
improbably, the most common favorite for a father is the last-born daughter.
وجدت أنه غالبا ما يكون الطفل المفضل عند الاباء هو أصغر البنات.
The most common favorite for a mother is the firstborn son.
وللأم هو أكبر الاولاد.
Now, this isn't Oedipal; never mind what the Freudians would have told us
حسنا هذه ليست عقدة أوديبية، لا تهتموا بما يقوله المهتمين بنظرية (فرويد)
a hundred years ago.
منذ مئة سنة.
And it's not just that fathers are habitually wrapped around
وأن الأباء عادة كالخواتم
the fingers of their little girls,
في أصابع بناتهم الصغيرات،
though I can tell you that, as the father of two girls,
بالرغم من أنني كأب لابنتين،
that part definitely plays a role.
أقول أن ذلك الجانب يلعب دورا مهما.
Rather, there is a certain reproductive narcissism at work.
ولكن ناك جانب أناني يعاد انتاجه.
Your opposite-gender kids
الأطفال من الجنس الآخر
can never resemble you exactly.
لا يمكن أن يشبهوك بشكل كامل.
But if somehow they can resemble you temperamentally,
ولكن إذا كانوا نوعا ما يشهبونك في المزاج،
you'll love them all the more.
ستحبهم أكثر.
As the result, the father who is a businessman will just melt
وكنتيجة، الأب رجل الأعمال سوف
at the idea of his MBA daughter with a tough-as-nails worldview.
يحب فكرة أن ابنته الحاصلة على أستاذية إدارة الأعمال لديها رؤى صلبة
The mother who is a sensitive type will go gooey over her son the poet.
والأم الحساسة ستحب ابنها الشاعر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Birth order, another topic I covered for TIME,
وترتيب الولادة، موضوع آخر، غطيته في مجلة التايم،
and another topic I cover in the book,
وكذلك في الكتاب،
plays out in other ways as well.
يلعب دورا أيضا.
Long before scientists began looking at this,
قبل أن يبدأ العلماء بالانتباه للأمر،
parents noticed that there are certain temperamental templates
لاحظ الأباء أن هناك قوالب مزاجية معينة
associated with all birth rankings:
تخص ترتيب الولادة:
the serious, striving firstborn;
الابن الجاد المكافح الأول،
the caught-in-a-thicket's middle born;
والأبن الوسط الذي
the wild child of a last born.
ثم الابن الجامح الأخير.
And once again, when science did crack this field,
ثم عندما تبحر العلماء بهذا المجال،
they found out mom and dad are right.
وجدوا أن الأمهات والأباء على حق.
Firstborns across history have tended to be bigger and healthier
فالابناء البكر على مر التاريخ يميلون لأن يكونوا أكبر جسديا وأكثر صحة
than later borns,
أكثر من الآخرين،
in part, because of the head start they got on food
جزئيا، لأنهم الأكبر يحصلون على الطعام
in an area in which it could be scarce.
في مناطق قد تكون نادرة.
Firstborns are also vaccinated more reliably
يتم اعطاءهم اللقاحات بانتظام
and tend to have more follow-up visits to doctors
ويذهبون بهم في مواعيد متابعة للأطباء
when they get sick.
عندما يمرضون.
And this pattern continues today.
ويستمر هذا الأمر حتى يومنا هذا.
This IQ question is, sadly -- I can say this as a second-born --
سؤال الـIQ هذا يقول بشكل محزن..
a very real thing.
شيئ حقيقي للغاية.
Firstborns have a three-point IQ advantage over second borns
فالابناء البكر لديهم معدلات IQ أعلى من الابناء الآخرين.
and second borns have a 1.5 IQ advantage over later borns,
والابناء بعد البكر لديهم تفوق في الIQ أكثر من البقية الأصغر،
partly because of the exclusive attention firstborns get from mom and dad,
وجزئيا هذا بسبب الانتباه الحصري الذي يحصل عليه الابناء البكر،
and partly because they get a chance to mentor the younger kids.
وجزئيا لأنهم حصلوا على فرصة في مراقبة أشقائهم الأصغر.
All of this explains why firstborns are likelier to be CEOs,
وهذا يفسر لمَ يمسك الابناء البكر غالبا منصاب كمدراء تنفيذيون،
they are likelier to be senators,
أو كحكام،
they are likelier to be astronauts,
أو كرواد فضاء،
and they are likelier to earn more than other kids are.
ويجنون مالا أكثر من البقية.
Last borns come into the world with a whole different set of challenges.
يأتي الابناء الأصغر وأمامهم تحديات مختلفة تماما.
The smallest and weakest cubs in the den,
أصغر وأضعف من في العش،
they're at the greatest risk of getting eaten alive,
وهم من يتعرض لخطر الالتهام أحياء،
so they have to develop what are called "low-power skills" --
لهذا عليهم تطوير ما يدعى "مهارات منخفضة القوى"..
the ability to charm and disarm,
قدرة السحر ونزع السلاح،
to intuit what's going on in someone else's head,
فهم ما يدور في روؤس الآخرين،
the better to duck the punch before it lands.
صد الهجمة قبل أن تصل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They're also flat-out funnier,
وهم بصراحة مرحين أكثر،
which is another thing that comes in handy,
وهو شيء يساعدهم كثيرا،
because a person who's making you laugh is a very hard person to slug.
لأن من يجعلك تضحك يصعب عليك تعنيفه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's perhaps no coincidence that over the course of history,
ولا مصادفه في أنه عبر الزمن،
some of our greatest satirists --
أعظم الهجاؤون..
Swift,
(سويفت)،
Twain,
(توين)،
Voltaire,
(فولتير)،
Colbert --
(كولبرت)..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
are either the last borns
كانوا الأصغر في عائلاتهم
or among the last in very large families.
أو من ضمن الأصغر في عائلاتهم الكبيرة.
Most middle borns don't get quite as sweet a deal.
ولا يحصل الذين ولدوا في الوسط على هذه الصفقات.
I think of us as the flyover states.
أفكر بنا كما لو أننا ولايات منخفضة الأهمية.
We are --
نحن..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
we're the ones who fight harder for recognition in the home.
من نحارب بشراسة ليتم الاعتراف بنا في المنزل.
We're the ones who are always raising our hands
نحن من يرفع أيدينا دوما
while someone else at the table is getting called on.
بينما ينادون شخصا آخر غيره.
We're the ones who tend to take a little longer
ونحن من نتأخر
to find their direction in life.
في إيجاد طريقنا في الحياة.
And there can be self-esteem issues associated with that,
ولدينا بعض المشاكل في احترام الذات،
notwithstanding the fact that I've been asked to do TED,
على الرغم من حقيقة أنني دعيت للمشاركة بتيد،
so I feel much better about these things right now.
أشعر بشعور أفضل الآن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the upside for middle borns is that they also tend to develop
ولكن الجانب الجميل لهم أنهم يميلون إلى تطوير
denser and richer relationships outside the home.
علاقات أعمق وأكثر كثافة خارج المنزل.
But that advantage comes also from something of a disadvantage,
ولكن هذا الميزة أتت من عيب،
simply because their needs weren't met as well in the home.
لأن احتياجاتهم لم يتم الايفاء بها في المنزل.
The feuds in the playroom that play out over favoritism,
العداء في غرفة الألعاب على حساب المحاباة،
birth order and so many other issues
وترتيب الولادة وقضايا أخرى
are as unrelenting as they seem.
هي حازمة كما تبدو.
In one study I cite in the book,
وفي دراسة استشهد بها في هذا الكتاب،
children in the two-to-four age group
أن الأطفال من عمر الثانية إلى الرابعة
engage in one fight every 6.3 minutes,
يدخلون في عراك كل 6.3 دقائق،
or 9.5 fights an hour.
أو 9.5 في الساعة.
That's not fighting -- that's performance art.
وهذا ليس عراكا.. بل هو ممارسة أحد الفنون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's extraordinary.
هذا مذهل.
One reason for this is that there are a lot more people in your home
وسببه أن هناك الكثير من الأشخاص في منزلك
than you think there are,
أكثر مما تظن،
or at least a lot more relationships.
أو على الأقل علاقات أخرى كثيرة.
Every person in your house has a discrete one-on-one relationship
كل شخص لديه علاقة مميزة
with every other person,
مع كل شخص آخر،
and those pairings or dyads add up fast.
وهذه الأزواج تتكون بسرعة.
In a family with two parents and two kids, there are six dyads:
في عائلة تتكون من زوجين وطفلين، هناك ست أزواج:
Mom has a relationship with child A and B,
الأم لها علاقة مع الطفل أ و ب،
Dad has a relationship with child A and B.
الأب له علاقة مع الطفل أ و ب.
There's the marital relationship,
والعلاقة الزوجية،
and there is the relationship between the kids themselves.
والعلاقة بين الطفلين نفسهما.
The formula for this looks very chilly but it's real.
شكل هذه العلاقات يبدو باردا ولكنه حقيقي.
K equals the number of people in your household,
حرف الكاف يساوي رقم الأشخاص في منزلك،
and X equals the number of dyads.
و أكس يساوي رقم الأزواج.
In a five-person family, there are ten discrete dyads.
وفي عائلة من خمس أشخاص، هناك عشرة أزواج.
The eight-person Brady Bunch -- never mind the sweetness here --
وفي عائلة (برادي بونش) ذو الثمانية أشخاص.. لا تهتموا باللطافة هنا..
there were 28 dyads in that family.
كان هناك 28 زوج في هذه العائلة.
The original Kennedy family with nine kids had 55 different relationships.
كان هناك 55 علاقة مختلفة في عائلة (كيندي) ذو التسعة أطفال.
And Bobby Kennedy, who grew up to have 11 children of his own,
وكان ل(بوبي كيندي) 11 طفلا،
had a household with a whopping 91 dyads.
ففي منزله 91 زوج.
This overpopulation of relationships
كثرة هذه العلاقات
makes fights unavoidable.
تجعل الشجارات أمرا لا مفر منه.
And far and away the biggest trigger for all sibling fights is property.
والسبب الأكبر لشجارات الأخوة هي الملكية.
Studies have found that over 95 percent of the fights among small children
فقد كشفت الدراسات أن 95% من الشجارات بين الأطفال
concern somebody touching, playing with,
تخص شخص قد لمس أو لعب بـ
looking at the other person's stuff.
أو نظر إلى ممتلكات شخص آخر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This in its own way is healthy if it's very noisy,
وهو أمر صحي
and the reason is that small children come into the world
والسبب هو أن هؤلاء الأطفال أتوا إلى العالم
with absolutely no control.
دون أي قدرة تحكم
They are utterly helpless.
فهم عاجزون تماما.
The only way they have of projecting their very limited power
والطريقة الوحيدة لفرض قوتهم المحدودة
is through the objects they can call their own.
من خلال الأدوات التي يمكنهم تملكها.
When somebody crosses that very erasable line,
وعندما يتخطى أحدهم ذلك الحاجز الذي يمكن مسحه،
they're going to go nuts, and that's what happens.
سيجنون وهذا ما يحدث.
Another very common casus belli among children is the idea of fairness,
سبب آخر بين الأطفال هي فكرة العدالة،
as any parent who hears 14 times a day, "But that's unfair!"
وكأي أب يسمع 14 مرة في اليوم جملة "ولكن هذا ليس عدلا"
can tell you.
يمكنه اخباركم بهذا.
In a way this is good, too, though.
وهذا بطريقة ما جيد.
Kids are born with a very innate sense of right and wrong,
فالأطفال يولدون بحس للصح والخطأ،
of a fair deal versus an unfair one,
لصفقه عادلة وصفقه غير عادلة،
and this teaches them powerful lessons.
ويعلمهم هذا دروسا قوية.
Do you want to know how powerfully encoded fairness is in the human genome?
هل تريدون معرفة مدى قوة العدل في جينات البشر؟
We process that phenomenon
نحن نطور الظاهرة
through the same lobe in our brain that processes disgust,
بنفس الطريقة التي يعالج فيها الدماغ عملية الهضم،
meaning we react to the idea of somebody being cheated
بمعنى أننا نتعامل مع خيانة أحدهم
the same way we react to putrefied meat.
مثلما نتعامل مع تناول قطعة من اللحم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Any wonder that this fellow, Bernie Madoff, is unpopular?
ونتساءل لمَ هذا الشخص (بيرني مادوف) غير مشهور؟
All of these dramas played out day to day,
كل هذه الدراما التي تم لعبها يوم بعد يوم،
moment to moment,
لحظة بعد لحظة،
serve as a real-time, total-immersion exercise for life.
تخدم في الوقت الحالي كتدريب بإنخراط كامل مدى الحياة
Siblings teach each other conflict avoidance and conflict resolution,
يعلم الأخوة بعضهم تجنب النزاعات والقرارات المترتبة على النزاعات،
when to stand up for themselves,
متى يدافعون عن نفسهم،
when to stand down;
متى لا يدافعون عن نفسهم،
they learn love,
يتعلمون الحب،
loyalty, honesty, sharing, caring, compromise,
الاخلاص والصدق والمشاركة، والاهتمام والتسوية
the disclosure of secrets and much more important,
الإباحة بالأسرار والأكثر أهمية
the keeping of confidences.
كتم الأسرار.
I listen to my young daughters -- aren’t they adorable? --
استمع إلى ابنتي الصغيرتين.. أليستا جميلتين؟..
I listen to my young daughters talking late into the night,
استمع إليهن يتحدثن بالليل،
the same way my parents, no doubt, listened to my brothers and me talking,
بالطريقة وبدون شك التي استمع بها أبي وأمي لي أنا وأخوتي
and sometimes I intervene, but usually I don't.
وبعض الأحيان أتدخل ولكن عادة لا أفعلها.
They're part of a conversation I am not part of,
هما في حديث لست جزء منه،
nobody else in the world is part of,
لا أحد في العالم جزء منه،
and it's a conversation that can and should go on
وهو حديث يمكنه ويجب عليه
for the rest of their lives.
أن يستمر لحياتهما بكاملها.
From this will come a sense of constancy,
ومن هنا يأتي حس الإستقرار،
a sense of having a permanent traveling companion,
حس بوجود رفيق سفر دائم،
somebody with whom they road-tested life
شخص معه تذوقوا الحياة
before they ever had to get out and travel it on their own.
قبل أن يخرجوا إلى العالم ويسافروا لوحدهم.
Brothers and sisters aren't the sine qua non of a happy life;
الأخوة والأخوات هم شرط لا غنى عنه لعيش حياة السعيدة،
plenty of adult sibling relationships are fatally broken
الكثير من علاقات الأخوه البالغين محطمة
and need to be abandoned for the sanity of everybody involved.
ويجب أن تهجر لتحافظ على سلامة كل من هو معهما.
And only-children, throughout history, have shown themselves
ولكن الأطفال وحدهم عبر التاريخ
to be creatively, brilliantly capable
أثبتوا أنهم خلاقون وقادرون بمهارة
of getting their socialization and comradeship skills
على الحصول على مهارات الاجتماع والرفقة
through friends, through cousins, through classmates.
مع أصدقائهم وابناء عمومتهم وزملائهم بالصف
But having siblings and not making the most of those bonds
ولكن أن يكون لديك أخوة ولا تستفيد من هذه الروابط
is, I believe, folly of the first order.
اعتقد أنه جنون.
If relationships are broken and are fixable, fix them.
إذا كانت العلاقات محطمة ولكن قابلة للاصلاح، اصلحها.
If they work, make them even better.
إذا نجح الأمر، أجعلها أفضل.
Failing to do so is a little like having a thousand acres of fertile farmland
الفشل في عمل هذا كالحصول على أرض زراعية
and never planting it.
دون زراعتها.
Yes, you can always get your food at the supermarket,
نعم، يمكنك الحصول على طعامك من المتجر
but think what you're allowing to lie fallow.
ولكن فكر كيف تفسد ارضك.
Life is short, it's finite, and it plays for keeps.
الحياة قصيرة ومنتهية،
Siblings may be among the richest harvests of the time we have here.
فربما يكون الأشقاء أوفر محاصيل الوقت الذي نعيشه الآن.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)